Lian Po...
（蒙恬(もうてん)）廉頗(れんぱ)が負けを認めた？
admitted his defeat?!
（信(しん)）えっ… 勝ったのか？
We... won?
（信）俺たちが…
Victory... And...
What are you saying, my lord?!
（介子坊(かいしぼう)）
何をおっしゃるのですか 殿！
勝負は まだ決しておりませぬぞ！
Victory or defeat has certainly not yet been decided!
If we slay Meng Ao, the state of battle will be even!
蒙驁(もうごう)を討ち取れば 戦況は五分
そこから今度こそ殿が大将となって
立て直せば 勝機は必ず…
And then, if we regroup with you as the Great General, my lord,
our victory will be certain!
That's right!
（魏(ぎ)兵）そうだ！ ここには
廉頗将軍と介子坊将軍がおられる！
We have both General Lian Po and General Jie Zifang here!
（魏兵）蒙驁を討つのは たやすい
Slaying Meng Ao will be an easy task!
Let's do it, General!
（魏兵）やりましょう 将軍！
（蒙恬）ンッ…
That's right! We can still win!
（魏兵）そうです！ まだ勝てます
（信）クッ… てめえら
You guys...
It's useless.
（廉頗）ムダじゃ
This war is already over.
この戦は もう詰んでおる
The war... is over?
戦が詰んでる？
If you take a look at the battlefield as a whole...
（廉頗）戦場全体を見渡せば―
Left Army
State of
Qin Army
Head Quarters
Central Army
Right Army
介子坊の左軍の ほとんどは
いまだ 山中に散ったまま
Right now Jie Zifang's left army is still scattered throughout the mountains.
中央軍は輪虎(りんこ)を失い もはや力なく
With the central army having lost Lun Hu, it's now powerless.
And Jiang Yan's right army has fallen back to the mountains.
姜燕(きょうえん)の右軍も 後方の山中にある
If we had enough time, we, the State of Wei Army could regroup.
それなりの時があれば
わしは魏国軍をここから立て直せる
But there is a factor that will not allow that.
しかし それを許さぬ存在がある
The man watching over the state of battle in a the mountain fortress far in the rear,
後方の山城の中で
じっと戦況を見守っている王翦(おうせん)じゃ
Wang Jian.
With his army's power largely undamaged, he is awaiting a chance to sortie.
（廉頗）ヤツは
軍の力をほぼ無傷に保ったまま―
出撃の機会をうかがっておる
この状況で 全力で戦える万の軍が
出現するというのは 決定打となる
With the battle in this state, the appearance of an army of 10,000, fully able to fight, would be a decisive blow.
Wang Jian... Wang Ben's dad, huh?
王翦… 王賁(おうほん)の親父(おやじ)か
But for Wang Jian, we have Jiang Yan...
しかし 王翦に対しては姜燕が…
（廉頗）足止め程度じゃ
Just enough to stop him.
If Wang Jian acts, he's certain to go after me.
王翦が出てくれば―
わしは 必ず背を追われ
全軍の立て直しが利かなくなる
And then I won't be able to reorganize our armies.
With the many armies scattered all over, Huan Ji will ruthlessly mow them down
そして バラバラになった各軍を
桓騎(かんき)が 冷酷に刈り取っていき…
and the State of Wei Army will be annihilated.
魏国軍は全滅じゃ
（介子坊）グッ…
If we're considering the best interest of the State of Wei, we must avoid that at all costs.
魏国のことを考えるなら
それだけは回避せねばならぬ
しかし！
But...
Go!
（壁(へき)）
行けー！ 蒙驁将軍を助けるのだ！
Save General Meng Ao!
A fresh supply of State of Qin soldiers are coming!
下から秦国(しんこく)の新手が来ます！
その数 およそ2,000！
They look to be... about 2,000!
（隊長）な… なに！
What?!
General!
将軍！
（介子坊）クッ…
Jie Zifang!
（廉頗）介子坊！
（介子坊）ハッ…
It's over.
終わりじゃ
My lord...
殿…
All right!
しゃ！ 今度こそ…
This time we...
We're making peace, Meng Ao!
和睦じゃ 蒙驁！
Peace...?
（朱可）和睦？
（廉頗）
これより 魏兵への攻撃を禁止する
I hereby forbid any further attacks on State of Wei soldiers!
I will promptly retreat the State of Wei Army!
魏国軍は
わしが速やかに退却させる
山陽(さんよう)近辺の住人も 退避させるゆえ
これにも手を出すな
I will also be evacuating the people living in the area of Shanyang, so do not touch them, either!
Make sure you don't loosen the reigns on Huan Ji!
特に 桓騎の手綱を緩めるなよ
うぬの責任じゃぞ！
He's your responsibility!
Th-These are peace negotiations?!
こ… これは和睦交渉なのか？
しかし 何の記しもなしに…
しかも この場合…
But there aren't any scribes or anything. He's doing it in this situation?
Normally, the winners are the ones that decide the conditions for peace.
和睦の条件とは
普通 勝者が決めるのじゃがのぅ
Pipe down!
やかましい！
命があるだけ ありがたいと思え！
You should be thankful that you're
getting out of this with your life!
Okay, make a quick decision.
さあ 即決せい　さもなくば―
Otherwise I'll have to kill you all before the reinforcements arrive!
新手が来る前に
貴様ら全員 皆殺しじゃ
Make sure you understand, I'm the one compromising here.
言っておくが譲歩してやってるのは
わしのほうじゃぞ
フン… 十分 分かっておるわい
I'm well aware of that.
（蒙驁）フォ…
Understood! I hear the terms for peace as stated by the State of Wei Army representative Lian Po,
相分かった！
魏国軍代表 廉頗の和睦申し入れ
秦国軍総大将 蒙驁が
受け入れようぞ！
and as Supreme Commander of the State of Qin Army, I, Meng Ao, accept them!
（どよめき）
えっ… これって…
S-So then...
The establishment of peace signifies the end of a war.
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
和睦の成立は 戦の終結を意味する
In other words, at this moment, the State of Qin's victory was decided.
つまり―
この瞬間
秦国軍の勝利が決まったのである
（尾平(びへい)）ハッ…
ま… まさか…
Could it be?!
L-Lord Ben.
（番陽(ばんよう)）ほ… 賁(ほん)さま
（王賁）フン…
I humbly apologize.
（介子坊）申し訳ありません…
The cause of our defeat was that I lose track of Huan Ji...
敗戦の責は 桓騎を見失った私に…
It was not Huan Ji.
桓騎ではない
（介子坊）はぁ？
Sir?
魏国軍の主力にして
土台であった中央軍
The central army which was the foundation of the State of Wei's main force...
あれが健在ならば立て直しは図れた
If it were still going strong, then we could have devised a regrouping.
The biggest mistake in my calculations was General Lun Hu getting slain by as-of-yet unknown soldiers.
最大の誤算は その将 輪虎が―
まだ無名の者たちに
討たれたことじゃ
Oh, right.
おお そうじゃった
How about we settle a matter here?
こっちは こっちで
話をつけておこうかのぅ
Meng Tian, get back.
蒙恬 下がってろ…
Xin...
信…
You want payback for Lun Hu, right?
輪虎の落とし前ってわけか
What, youngster?
なんじゃ 童(わっぱ)
貴様 見た目以上に頭が悪いのぅ
You're even dumber than you look.
な… なに！
Wh-What?!
Do Lun Hu or I look like men of such small caliber?
わしや輪虎が
そんなに器の小さい男に見えるか？
Then, what?!
じゃ 何の…
You said it before, didn't you?
先ほど申しておったろう
王騎が 貴様に矛を受け取らせたと
That you received Wang Qi's lance.
That means that you are someone that chases after Wang Qi,
…ということは
貴様は 王騎の背を追う者
someone that seeks to be a Great General.
大将軍を目指す者
…ということになる
フッ…
見るからに その低そうな身分でな
But from the looks of you, you're of pretty low birth, eh?
Low birth doesn't—
身分なんて関係…
（廉頗）ああ 関係ない
Yeah, it doesn't matter!
What you need in order to become a Great General
大将軍になるために必要なものは
百の精神力！
is great "force of will"!
And great physical strength!
そして 百の腕力！ 更に 百の知恵
And great wisdom!
それから 百の経験と 百の幸運！
And then you need great experience and great luck!
Th-That's a lot...
（信）お… 多い
The State of Zhao Three Great Devas and the State of Qin Six Great Generals had all of those things.
それら全てを兼ね備えた
趙国三大天(ちょうこく さんだいてん)と秦国六大将軍は―
かつて
正に完璧(かんぺき)な時代を築き上げた
And at one time... we constructed the perfect era!
I guess since I'm the only one that survived it, I must have been the strongest!
その中で 唯一 生き残った わしは
結局 最強だったということかのぅ
まあ それは いいとして
Well, though about that, youngster.
童…
（信）ハッ…
Do you seriously think you can become my equal?
そんな わしらと 貴様は―
本気で 肩を並べるようになれると
思っておるのか？
ヘッ… だから 言ってんだろう
I told you, didn't I?
My dream ain't something half-assed like that!
俺の夢は そんな半端じゃねえって
（廉頗）うん？
I won't be your equal!
肩を並べるんじゃねえ
I'll blow through you guys
俺は あんたらをぶち抜いて
史上最強の天下の大将軍になるんだ
and I'll become strongest general in all of history under the heavens!
聞いたか？ 介子坊
（介子坊）はぁ…
Ya hear that, Jie Zifang?
Yes, sir.
いや 悪くないぞ 小僧
Naw, not bad, kid.
For the first time in a while, your intensity made me remember what we were like in our younger days.
今の感じは 久しぶりに若きころの
わしたちの姿を思い出した
All right. Seeing as you know so little, I'll tell you something.
よかろう　ものを知らぬ貴様に
ひとつだけ教えておいてやる
貴様は
わしらを追い抜くことも―
It is not possible for you to surpass us or equal us!
わしらと
肩を並べることも できはしない
What?!
なんだと…
That scorching era is already undeniably the stuff of legend!
強烈すぎた あの時代は
もはや かげることなき伝説
故に これから先
いかに貴様らが暴れ回ろうと―
So no matter how you bastards rampage across this land,
常に疑問を呈される
（信）ンッ…
it will always be questioned.
In other words, you'll wonder "How would this have gone if they lived in this era?"
すなわち“彼らが
もし この時代にいたならば”とな
W-What?! But there's nothing we can do about that!
そ… そんな！ んなの 俺らには
どうしようもねえことじゃねえか
Exactly.
そのとおりじゃ
Our legends are protected by the flow of time.
わしらの伝説は 時の流れに
守られてしまったからのぅ
ンッ… 証明の…
There's no way...
（蒙恬）しようがない…
...to prove it.
But there is actually one way to surpass us.
じゃが 実は ひとつだけ
わしらを抜く方法が存在する
えっ？
な… 何だよ？ その方法って
Wh-What is it?!
フッ… 伝説の塗り替えじゃ
Blow away the legends.
If you achieve something great that even we could not achieve,
わしらでも なしえなかった大業を
やってのければ―
history will surely revere you!
歴史は 必ず貴様らをあがめる
（信）なしえなかった大業…
Something great no one's ever done before?
Yeah.
The uniting of China.
中華の統一じゃ
Xin
The uniting... of China...?
中華の… 統一
Th-That's something a bit too disconnected from reality...
そ… それは…
あまりにも現実離れした大業だ
Exactly. It's been 500 years since we entered this world of warring states.
そのとおりじゃ　戦乱の世に
突入して500年じゃからのぅ
To achieve that, a king with great military power and the caliber to use it...
それを成すには―
すさまじい武の力と
それを振るう器
as well as the caliber to accept the karma of great, bloody deeds must appear.
血の大業の業を受け止める器を
持つ王が 出現せねばならん
That's impossible.
ムリだ　伝説の武王(ぶおう)をも超える
そんな覇業に挑む王など―
There's no way a king that will make a bid for supremacy like that, even surpassing the legendary King Wu, could emerge...
出てくるはずが…
（信）いや ムリじゃねえ
No, it's not impossible.
No, it's not impossible, Meng Tian.
ムリなんかじゃねえぞ 蒙恬
Uniting China. There is someone who has boasted that that is their defined path...
“中華統一” それを 自分の確かな
道だって豪語しやがったのが―
our current king!
今の俺たちの王さまだ！
It's a promise, General Lian Po!
約束だぞ 廉頗将軍！
Uniting China! That'll be proof that we've surpassed you guys!
中華統一！ それが
俺らが あんたらを超えた証しだ！
ウワッ…
（どよめき）
Give it your all to devote yourself to that.
せいぜい精進せい　じゃあな
So long, Xin of the Feixin Unit.
飛信(ひしん)隊 信
H-Hey, Lun Hu's sword!
おい！ 輪虎の剣は？
He's clearly telling you to take it.
それは
お前が持っとけってことだろう
Oh... I guess so...
そっか…
そうだな
I have nothing to talk to you about.
貴様と話すことなどないわ
（蒙驁）フォ？
フォフォ… そう言うなて
公式の和議もろもろ ある
Don't say that!
There are all kinds of peace negotiations.
両軍 少し落ち着いたら
そのとき ゆっくり語ろうて…
There are all kinds of formal arrangements to make.
Once both armies have calmed down, we—
Send a representative!
代理を送る
（蒙驁）フォ？
蒙驁 どういう形にせよ
まんまと やりおったな
Meng Ao... In whatever form it may be in, you've squarely beaten me.
There are many major positions across China,
この中華に
主要拠点は いくつかあるが
but this Shanyang is honestly a huge one.
ここ山陽は誠に でかいぞ
うむ…
My feelings of taking you down for the sake of the State of Wei were not false.
（廉頗）魏国のために 貴様らを
返り討ちにしてやろうと思ったのは
偽りなき本心
I can't face the state's king now.
国王に合わす顔がないわ
So now you can finally lay down your lance, eh, Lian Po?
これで やっと矛が置けるな 廉頗
フッ… わしのおかげで
Thanks to me!
Don't talk nonsense.
（廉頗）バカを言え
I'll be on active duty until I die!
わしは死ぬまで現役じゃ！
帰るぞ！
（介子坊）ははっ！
Let's go home!
Yes, sir!
Uniting China...
（信）中華の統一…
You finally did it, eh, General Meng Ao!
ついにやったな 蒙驁将軍
No matter how it happens, a win's a win!
何だって勝ちは勝ちだ
大逆転じゃねえか
You got your big comeback!
将軍 早く手当てを
General, hurry, your wounds must be tended to.
Wait, wait. Later, later.
待て待て　あとあと
（信･蒙恬）あっ…
This comes first.
（蒙驁）まずは何より これじゃ
In this war, the State of Qin has been victorious!
この戦 秦国軍が勝利したぞー！
（崇原(すうげん)･松左(しょうさ)）しゃ！
All right!
We did it! We did it!
（尾平）
やった！ やったぞ！ ハハハッ！
It's regrettable.
無念です…
If only you had been there, Lord Ben, I am sure you could have rendered some achievements!
あの場に賁さまがおられれば
必ずや 武功を上げられたはず
（王賁）当然だ
Of course.
だが この地で 激烈な魏国の軍勢を
せき止められるのは―
But only the Yufeng Unit was able to halt the fervent State of Wei Army forces here.
玉鳳(ぎょくほう)隊以外なかった
Do not fear. I will not yield next time.
案ずるな　次は譲らない
Boss! It looks like they reached the conclusion!
（手下）
お頭！ 決着ついたようですぜ
I can see that on my own.
（桓騎）見りゃ分かるよ
I'm looking forward to the reward.
（桓騎）論功が楽しみだな
（手下たち）ヘヘヘヘッ…
Lord Jiang Yan.
（副将）姜燕さま…
（姜燕）帰るぞ
（副将）ははっ…
We're going home.
Yes, sir!
（王翦）フン…
ハハハッ… すげえ熱気だ
もう１戦いけんじゃねえか？
It sure is intense around here!
Kinda feels like you could last another battle, doesn't it?
信 すげえ顔色悪いぞ
お前は ここで寝てろ
Xin, your complexion looks really bad.
You should rest here.
Don't be an idiot.
バカ言え
今から下行って みんなと…
I've gotta head down and celebrate with everyone...
Xin, is that you?
信！ 信か？
（信）えっ？
あっ！ 壁のあんちゃ…
Brother Bi!
X-Xin! What's wrong?!
（壁）し… 信！ どうした？
He's not breathing?!
（蒙恬）ゲッ！ こいつ 息してない
救護兵！ 救護兵！
Aid soldiers! Aid soldiers!
R-Report! Report!
（伝令）ほ… 報告！
報告ーっ！
も… 蒙驁軍 勝利！
蒙驁軍 勝利です！
The Meng Ao Army... is victorious!
The Meng Ao Army is victorious!
（昌文君(しょうぶんくん)）ハァ…
All right!
（廷臣）よ～し！
やってくれたな 白老大将軍
The White Elder Great General did it, eh?!
…ということは あの廉頗を！
（廷臣）ハハハッ！
That means the Lian Po was...
What a spectacular victory!
大金星だな！
（廷臣）祝杯じゃ 祝杯！
This calls for a celebratory drink!
Good...
（昌平君(しょうへいくん)）よし…
Do you know the details of the war?
（呂不韋(りょふい)）
戦の詳細は分からんのか？
武功を上げたのは誰じゃ？
Who rendered the big achievements?
Yes, sir. It was general Huan Ji sending this information.
（伝令）はっ！
伝わってきているのは桓騎将軍です
敵の参謀と総大将の２人を討ち取り
勝利を決したと！
His defeating of an enemy staff officer and their Supreme Commander is what decided the victory!
（呂不韋）
おお なんと あの盗賊が？
Oh. That thief did, eh?
And next is the one that slew the general of the enemy central army, Lun Hu.
（伝令）そして次いで 中央軍の
将である輪虎を討ち取った―
It was a Thousand-Man General named Xin of the Feixin Unit.
飛信隊の信という千人将です！
（政(せい)）なっ…
I don't know who that is, but he did well.
（呂不韋）誰か知らんが
ようやった ハハハハッ！
I see...
そうか…
You did it, Xin!
やったな 信！
H-Honestly?!
（文官）ま… 誠か！
The General Lian Po was defeated?!
（文官）
あの廉頗将軍が敗れたのか？
（カイネ）
ハッ… 李牧(りぼく)さまの読みが外れた？
Lord Li Mu's prediction was off?
So they took Shanyang, did they?
（李牧）山陽を取られたか…
Depending on the State of Qin's attitude,
（李牧）秦国の出方しだいでは
ここから 天下は大きく荒れますよ
there may be some major changes in the world soon.
Having defeated the State of Wei Army,
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）魏国軍を破った秦国軍は
山陽一帯の平定のため 多くが
臨戦態勢のまま その地に残った
the State of Qin Army left many in that area prepared for battle in order to subjugate the Shanyang region.
Meanwhile, the wounded soldiers started on the road back to the State of Qin.
一方で 傷の重い兵たちは
秦国への帰路に就いた
And with the Feixin Unit was the modest reward given to them by Meng Ao.
飛信隊が その中に入れられたのは
蒙驁の ささやかな褒美であった
It was a journey of about one month to reach their home.
故郷までの道のりは およそ ひと月
Though on the way there, many wounded soldiers passed away before they reached their destination.
道中 多くの負傷兵が もたずに
息を引き取ったが
The soldiers returning home victorious were by no means heavy-footed.
それでも勝者として帰る兵士たちの
足取りは 決して重くはなかった
（羌瘣(きょうかい)）ンッ… ンン…
そうか 終わったんだな
I see. So it's over?
And there was one person saying goodbye in a different way...
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）そして
別の形で別れようとする者が―
ひとり
（昂(こう)）あっ！
（尾平）羌瘣！
Qiang Lei!
（慶(けい)）羌瘣副長！
Vice Captain Qiang Lei!
You're awake?!
め… 目が覚めたのか
ずっと寝てたんだぞ お前
大丈夫か？
You were sleeping for a really long time, are you okay?!
Yeah, fine.
ああ 大丈夫
S-So cute!
（一同）か… かわいい
She really is cute!
（兵士）やっぱり かわいい…
（兵士）や… やべえぞ
Aw man, I can't take it!
（兵士）何だ？ この気持ち
What are these feelings?!
Hey, you bastards, don't give Qiang Lei those weird looks!
て… てめえら
変な目で羌瘣を見るんじゃねえ！
お前だって顔 真っ赤じゃねえか！
（兵士）そうだ そうだ！
Hey man, your face is bright red!
Yeah, that's right!
アア… うるせえ！
Sheddep!
Um, Qiang Lei, everybody knows you're a woman now...
い… いや 羌瘣
お前が女だってのは
もう みんな 知っててさ
We were surprised, but nothing's gonna change because of it.
驚いたけど… 別に
だからって 何も変わらねえんだ
Actually, to be honest, I'm kinda glad you're a woman...
逆に 女で良かったっつうか…
実は お… 俺 何度か 自分が
そっち系なのかって思うぐらい―
There were actually a few times when I thought I might be uh, that way, from the weird way I felt when looking at you.
お前のこと見て
変な気持ちになったことがあって…
What're you talking about, Mr. Ping?
（昂）尾平さん 何言ってんの？
いや だから…
Uh, so...
What I'm saying is everything's still gonna be the same way as always!
とにかく 何もかも
今までどおりだって言ってんだ！
Got it.
分かった
So cute!
（一同）かわいい…
Ms. Qiang Lei! Are you going to leave on your journey for revenge?
羌瘣さん！
敵討ちの旅に行っちゃうの？
Ah, I'm sorry. I heard it from Xin, so I was thinking a lot about it...
あっ ごめんなさい
信に聞いたから いろいろ…
べ… 別に止めはしねえよ 俺らは
We're not plannin' on stopping you or anything.
Just let us know when you're going. We wanna see you off.
ただ 行くときは言えよな
見送りてえからよ
Yeah.
Wei Ping, where is he?
尾平 あいつは？
Xin?
信か？
（羌瘣）うん
あいつも ひでえ傷で…
He had some pretty awful wounds, too.
But he's okay now.
でも 大丈夫だ
あと３日もすれば目を覚ますって
魯延(ろえん)じいが言ってた
Old man Lu Yan said he'd be awake after resting three days.
I see.
そうか
Tomorrow, before dawn, I'm leaving.
明日 夜明け前に たつ
If I head north on a boat floating by on the nearby Yang River tributary,
すぐそこに流れてる羊河(ようが)の支流を
舟で北上すれば―
I can go straight to the State of Zhao where my target of revenge is.
敵(かたき)のいる趙国に一気に入れるからだ
…て
薄暗い中 たつ理由には ならないな
Though that's not really a reason to leave while it's still dark out.
I just don't know what sort of face to put on to say goodbye to all of you.
今の私は どういう顔で お前たちと
別れればいいか分からない
A long time ago, I used to do things like laugh and cry,
昔は 普通に
泣いたり笑ったりしてたんだが
but when I found Big Sis Xiang's corpse, something broke inside me.
象(しょう)姉の亡骸(なきがら)を見つけたときに
何かが私の中で壊れた
I hope I go back to normal when I get revenge, but...
敵を討ったら元に戻るといいんだが
まあ …というわけで行く
Well, anyhow, I'm going.
Don't think badly of me.
悪く思うな
See ya.
じゃあな
I couldn't get a wink of sleep.
一睡もできなかった…
Yup, she fell.
やっぱり落ちた
You think you can get revenge like this?!
こんなんで敵討てんのか？ おい
アハハハッ！
（渕(えん)）は… 早く羌瘣どのに縄を！
Q-Quickly, get a rope for Lord Qiang Lei!
Hey. What the hell are you doing?
何のマネだ？ おい
ヘッ… 罰だ 罰
黙って１人で行こうとしやがって
That's punishment for trying to go alone without saying anything!
Anyhow, that part of you is really small.
（信）大体…
お前は その辺 ちっせえんだよ
泣こうが笑おうが
どっちだっていいっつうの
It doesn't matter if you laugh or cry.
With your heart being so feeble, there's one thing I wanna say to you...
そんな心の かよわいお前に
ひとつ言っておきてえことはよ
No matter how far away you are, you can bet we're supporting that small frame of yours.
どんだけ離れようと―
お前のちっせえ背中 俺たちが
ガッチリ支えてるからなってこった
ヘッ… 行ってこいよ
Now get going, Qia—
きょうか… ウワッ！
（兵士たち）羌瘣ーっ！
Qiang Lei!
Xin!
Lord Xin! Captain!
じゃあな
See ya.
Good luck!
頑張れよー！
（声援）
Preview
The Strategist Arrives
End